Finding Aid for David LeFavour photographs, circa 1894-circa. 1905
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David LeFavour photographs circa 1894-circa 1905
LeFavour, David, 1873-1910.
155 glass negatives
0.5 linear feet
92432 UA 2
Graduate of the University of Michigan College of Engineering, Class of 1895. Glass negatives and prints of scenes at the University of Michigan, including Alpha Delta Phi fraternity, the Engineering summer camp, football and baseball games, the track team, University buildings and campus scenes, and views of the Huron River; also views of Bay City, Michigan, and portraits of members of the LeFavour, Shearer, and McMillan families.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Susan Kraus of New Hartford, Connecticut (donor no. 6252 ). The collection came in two accessions, 1978 and 1982.
The collection is open to research.
David LeFavour was born on September 7, 1873, in Bay City, Michigan, and died at the age of thirty-seven, on August 10, 1910. He was the son of Edward and Martha Walker Hutchinson LeFavour. Edward LeFavour died on March 27, 1874, of a ruptured appendix, and David LeFavour and his younger sister Helen were orphaned when their mother died on September 29, 1878, while visiting in Pawtucket, Rhode Island.
Margaret Hutchinson Shearer, sister of David's mother and wife of James Shearer of Bay City, brought David and Helen LeFavour into her family. James Shearer served as regent of the University of Michigan from 1880 to 1888. He had built several family business interests: saw mills, banking, architecture, and real estate, into Shearer and Sons (later Shearer Brothers) of Bay City, Michigan. Shearer's activity in church and civic affairs combined with his construction efforts in and around Shearer Block on Center Street to make the family a leading force in local development.
In 1895 David LeFavour graduated from the University of Michigan with a B.S. degree in civil engineering. Some six years later he married Helen MacLaren Kline on December 5, 1901. They lived in Detroit, Michigan for a time, and had twin sons, David E. and William B., who were born on October 4, 1902.
David LeFavour's professional career is not well-documented, although according to The Technic, a publication of the University of Michigan Engineering Society, LeFavour was employed by the Detroit and Mackinaw Railway as a draughtsman (1896-1898) and by the Bay City Round Hoop Company (1898-?) as treasurer. Family sources also indicate that LeFavour invested in a vacuum cleaning company at one time.
Health problems plagued David LeFavour for some time, and he and his family often summered in Wallacebourg, Ontario, Canada. It was here that LeFavour suffered a fatal attack and died of what was later diagnosed as a ruptured appendix, similar to his father's illness.
LeFavour's interest and love of photography never went beyond that of an amateur, and can likely be traced to his academic work as an engineer, in which photography was used for surveying purposes. The actual surveying photographs and scenes of an engineering camp are further evidence of this possibility.
The David LeFavour glass negatives collection documents a variety of activities, individuals, groups, and buildings in Ann Arbor and Bay City. As a member of the class of 1895, a year which was, coincidently, the first year of formal recognition for a Department of Engineering at the University of Michigan, LeFavour participated in an annual event for engineering students. A summer camp was set up outside the University to conduct field projects. The camp was periodically relocated and in 1895 a change was made from a grove on the outskirts of Leland, Michigan, at an outlet of Carp Lake (now Lake Leelanau), to a point further up the lake near the Fountain Point Hotel.
The scenes of the camp and the engineers depict several projects undertaken by the group, their campsite and equipment, and members of the entourage, including Professor Joseph B. Davis (Geodesy and Surveying) who was in charge of the operation. LeFavour also captured his peers at play, as a print of a baseball game at nearby Sutton's Bay reveals.
As a student, David LeFavour was also a member of the Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity. He photographed his fraternity house, his room, an unidentified ceremony, and several group portraits of his fraternal brothers and their dates.
Although there is no indication of any personal participation by LeFavour in university athletics, he did photograph members of the university track team and local football games. Other negatives and prints detail several university buildings and more "artistic" views of the Huron River and local Ann Arbor streets.
Those negatives and prints focusing on Bay City, Michigan, provide an insight into another facet of LeFavour's life and interests. Several exterior views are present, which detail the various Shearer homes in the city as well as those of other prominent residents. Interior views of the James Shearer home (where David grew up), reflect the style of life and living conditions of a prosperous Michigan family at the turn of the century.
Many Bay City buildings, including schools, hospitals, and government structures are identified. As was done in Ann Arbor, LeFavour also photographed street views and individuals. Two favorite subjects for LeFavour were children and women. He frequently photographed young relatives and used his photographic skills to show his sister Helen in particular. Often the young lady (or ladies) were posed with bicycles.
The LeFavour negatives were randomly described and dated. Available information has been provided when possible, however. All negatives were produced between 1894 and 1895, but no dates have been attempted for undated negatives or prints. The print collection is numbered so that one can refer back to the appropriate glass negative. There are over 155 glass negatives and a corresponding number of prints.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alpha Delta Phi. Peninsular Chapter (University of Michigan); Baseball.; Bay City (Mich.)--Buildings.; Boats.; Buildings--Michigan--Bay City.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Camps.; Children.; Davis, Joseph Baker, 1845-1920.; Football.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Interiors.; LeFavour family.; McMillan family.; Shearer family.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Cyanotypes.; Photographs.
- Contact Prints And Other Photographs
  - University of Michigan
    - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity
      - Exteriors
        - Buildings (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Individuals and women (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Men (groups) (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Interiors
        - Groups and Formal Celebrations (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - College Room (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Department of Engineering
      - Engineering Camp
        - Boat landing (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Campsite and equipment (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Construction efforts (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Faculty (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - Groups (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Individuals (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - Recreation (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Surveying sites
        - Identified (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Athletics
      - Football games
        - 1894 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Track and Field: team members, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - University Buildings, exteriors, identified and unidentified (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Ann Arbor, Michigan
    - Views and landscapes
      - Huron River (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Michigan Central Railroad Station, and Michigan Central Railroad Station, Bay City (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Streets (identified and unidentified) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bay City, Michigan residences
    - Exteriors
      - James Shearer House (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Other Shearer Brothers' Houses (G. Henry and Chauncey H.) (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Other houses (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Interiors
      - James Shearer house (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - James Shearer house, 8 1/2" x 6 1/2" (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bay City, Michigan Buildings
    - Exteriors, identified (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bay City, Michigan Individuals
    - Children
      - Alfred Shearer (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Others (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Men
      - F.P. Graves, Mr. Carter, J. vanDuclusin (?) and others (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Women, Identified and unidentified (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bay City, Michigan Miscellaneous
    - Streets
      - Identified and unidentified (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Landscapes
      - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Family Photographs
    - Identified
      - David LeFavour Portrait (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Children, David E. and William B. LeFavour (twins) (Box 1, Folder 36)
        (includes cyanotypes)
    - Unidentified
      - Men and women (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Homes and landscapes (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - McMillan Family (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Shearer Family (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "David LeFavour, student photographer, 1894-1895" article with negative numbers noted (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Glass Negatives
  [Restricted access: Staff use only]
  (Stored in 1 folder and 3 wooden trays; availability of print is indicated by numbers in brackets [] referring to a folder in box 1)
  - James Shearer House, Bay City -- Interiors, 1-3); 8 1/2" x 6 1/2" (Box 2)
    [26]
  - Surveying Photograph-University of Michigan Campus, View of East University Street and Elementary School, 4); 5" x 8" (Box 2)
    [13]
  - Surveying Photograph-University of Michigan Campus, 5-9); 5" x 8" (Box 2)
    [14]
  - City Building, Bay City September, 1895, 10) (Box 2)
    [27]
  - Hospitals, University of Michigan, 11) (Box 2)
    [18]
  - F.P. Graves, 12) (Box 2)
    [31]
  - Presbyterian Church, Bay City, 13) (Box 2)
  - Masonic Temple, Bay City, 14) (Box 2)
  - Episcopal Church, Bay City September, 1895, 15) (Box 2)
  - High School, Bay City September, 1895, 16) (Box 2)
  - Elm Lawn Cemetery, Bay City September 1895, 17) (Box 2)
  - James vanDucusin (?), Bay City September, 1895, 18) (Box 2)
  - James Shearer House, Bay City-Interior September, 1895, 19) (Box 2)
    [25]
  - James Shearer House, Bay City-Interior September, 1895, 20) (Box 2)
  - G. Henry Shearer House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 21) (Box 2)
    [23]
  - Chauncey H. Shearer, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 22) (Box 2)
  - H.M.K. at McCormicks, 23) (Box 3)
  - Michigan Central Railroad Station, Bay City September, 1895, 24) (Box 2)
    [20]
  - Observatory, University of Michigan, 25) (Box 2)
  - H.M.K. at McCormicks, 26) (Box 3)
  - McEwan House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 27) (Box 2)
    [24]
  - Amelise and Alfred (Shearer), Bay City September, 1895, 28) (Box 2)
    [28]
  - Woodland Pond, Windfall Timber (with fisherman and boater), 29) (Box 2)
    [34]
  - Engineers and Tent (group), 30) (Box 2)
    [10]
  - Engineer and Tent (individual), 31) (Box 2)
    [11]
  - Tent and Equipment (?), 32) (Box 2)
    [7]
  - Campsite, 33) (Box 2)
  - Lakeshore, 34) (Box 2)
    [6]
  - Engineering class (group), 35) (Box 2)
    [8]
  - Couple with baby and carriage, 36) (Box 2)
  - Engineer and Tent (individual), 37) (Box 2)
    [9]
  - Boat, "The SALLIE," with engineers, 38) (Box 2)
    [16]
  - Engineers (group) at campsite, 39) (Box 2)
  - Engineers (group) and Tent, 40) (Box 2)
  - Building, 41) (Box 2)
  - City Street, 42) (Box 2)
    [33]
  - Engineer and Tent, 43) (Box 2)
  - Fraternity House, 44) (Box 2)
    [1]
  - Alfred Shearer, Bay City September, 1895, 45) (Box 2)
  - Campsite, Boat Landing June, 1895, 46) (Box 2)
  - Engineers (group) at roll call June, 1895, 47) (Box 2)
  - Baseball game at Sutton's Bay June, 1895, 48) (Box 2)
    [12]
  - Campsite, Building a Landing (swampwork) June, 1895, 49) (Box 2)
  - Engineers, starting out for Sutton's Bay June, 1895, 50) (Box 2)
  - Women (group), Helen, Margaret, and Jack (?) July, 1895, 51) (Box 2)
    [32]
  - Main Building, 52) (Box 2)
  - Unidentified Women July, 1895, 53) (Box 2)
  - Unidentified Building, 54) (Box 2)
  - Mr. Carter (Maltby Carter), Bay City September, 1895, 55) (Box 2)
  - C.A. Eddy House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 56) (Box 2)
  - Engineers, Clifford Moses Pritchard and David LeFavour June, 1895, 57) (Box 2)
  - Engineers (group) with instruments June, 1895, 58) (Box 2)
  - Surveying Camp June, 1895, 59) (Box 2)
  - Alfred Shearer, Bay City August, 1895, 60) (Box 2)
  - Alfred Shearer, Bay City August, 1895, 61) (Box 3)
  - Helen and Alfred Shearer August, 1895, 62) (Box 3)
  - Miss Beckwith and Bicycle July, 1895, 63) (Box 3)
  - Women (group), Helen, Margaret, and Jack M. July, 1895, 64) (Box 3)
  - Women (group), Helen, Margaret, and Jack (?) July, 1895, 65) (Box 3)
  - Engineers (group), 66) (Box 3)
    [3]
  - Tappan Hall, University of Michigan, 67) (Box 3)
  - Children (unidentified) with laundry basket, 68) (Box 3)
    [30]
  - Women (group), 69) (Box 3)
    [2]
  - Student room, University of Michigan (Alpha Delta Phi?), 70) (Box 3)
    [5]
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 71) (Box 3)
    [19]
  - Curtice (?) House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 72) (Box 3)
  - Fraternity House (group), 73) (Box 3)
  - Sunday Walk (group), 74) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity (group), 75) (Box 3)
    [4]
  - Fraternity House (group) 1895, 76) (Box 3)
  - Fraternity House (group) 1895, 77) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity (group), 78) (Box 3)
  - James Shearer House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 79) (Box 3)
    [22]
  - Lane Building, University of Michigan, 80) (Box 3)
  - Medical Building, University of Michigan, 81) (Box 3)
  - Professor Joseph B. Davis (Geodesy and Surveying), at Campsite June, 1895, 82) (Box 3)
  - The Whitfield Family (at campsite), 83) (Box 3)
  - F.E.E. (unknown woman) and bicycle August, 1895, 84) (Box 3)
  - Harriet E. M and bicycle August, 1895, 85) (Box 3)
    [29]
  - F.E.E. (unknown woman) August, 1895, 86) (Box 3)
  - F.E.E., N.J.D., and Harriet E. (?) August, 1895, 87) (Box 3)
  - N.J.D. (unknown woman) and bicycle August, 1895, 88) (Box 3)
  - Women (group) on fence (man in background) August, 1895, 89) (Box 3)
  - Harriet E. (?) and Elaine, 90) (Box 3)
  - Harriet E. M and Elaine, 91) (Box 3)
  - Miss Beckwith July, 1895, 92) (Box 3)
  - James Shearer House, Bay City-Exterior September, 1895, 93) (Box 3)
  - Government Building, Bay City September, 1895, 94) (Box 3)
  - Spencer O. Fisher House, Bay City Exterior September, 1895, 95) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House Interior, group at piano, 96) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Track Team (two members), 97) (Box 3)
    [17]
  - University of Michigan Track Team (individual), 98) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Track Team (individual), 99) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Track Team (cyclist and assistant), 100) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Track Team (individual), 101) (Box 3)
  - Football game, 102) (Box 3)
  - Engineers (group), 103) (Box 3)
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 104) (Box 3)
  - University Hall, University of Michigan, 105) (Box 3)
  - Three young men (unidentified), 106) (Box 3)
  - Students (group), on a cattle guard, Ann Arbor 1895, 107) (Box 3)
  - F.P. Graves, 108) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House (group), Commencement Week 1895, 109) (Box 3)
  - A.H. Wrigt (outside Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House) 1895, 110) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity (group?) October, 1895, 111) (Box 3)
  - Physical Lab, University of Michigan, 112) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House, Class of 1897, October, 1895, 113) (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Track Team (individual), 114) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House, Class of 1898, October, 1895, 115) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House, unidentified group, 116) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House-Interior, room of D. LeFavour and Robert Clark Stephens, 117) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House-Interior, group at formal celebration, 118) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House-Interior, group at formal celebration, 119) (Box 3)
  - Alpha Delta Phi Fraternity House-Interior, group at formal celebration, 120) (Box 3)
  - Bay City, Center Avenue west of Jefferson Avenue, 121) (Box 3)
  - Bay City, Center Avenue east of Madison Avenue, 122) (Box 3)
  - Waterman Gymnasium, University of Michigan, 123) (Box 3)
  - Delta Kappa Epsilon Fraternity, University of Michigan, 124) (Box 3)
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 125) (Box 3)
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 126) (Box 3)
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 127) (Box 3)
  - Football, 128) (Box 3)
  - Football, 129) (Box 3)
  - Football, 130) (Box 3)
  - Michigan Central Railroad Station, Ann Arbor, 131) (Box 3)
  - "Lower Town" Ann Arbor, 132) (Box 3)
    [21]
  - Huron River at Ann Arbor, 133) (Box 3)
  - Margaret (Shearer), Bay City September, 1895, 134) (Box 3)
  - Helen LeFavour (sister) and Margaret Shearer (cousin), Bay City September, 1895, 135) (Box 3)
  - Alfred Shearer, Bay City September, 1895, 136) (Box 3)
  - The three boys, Bay City September, 1895, 137) (Box 3)
  - Helen (LeFavour), Bay City September, 1895, 138) (Box 3)
  - Alfred Shearer, Bay City September, 1895, 139) (Box 3)
  - Engineers (group) with instruments June, 1895, 140) (Box 3)
  - Three Instructors, at engineers' camp June, 1895, 141) (Box 3)
  - Fountain, engineers' camp June, 1895, 142) (Box 3)
  - Bridge, engineers' camp June, 1895, 143) (Box 3)
  - Professor Davis and Tent June, 1895, 144) (Box 3)
  - Baseball at Sutton's Bay June, 1895, 145) (Box 3)
  - Engineers, Boat landing June, 1895, 146) (Box 3)
  - Mechanical Lab, University of Michigan, 147) (Box 3)
  - Broken Down House (near engineers' camp), 148) (Box 3)
  - Football, 149) (Box 3)
  - Football 1894, 150) (Box 3)
    [15]
  - Library, University of Michigan, 151) (Box 3)
  - "Semaphore Group" October, 1894, 152) (Box 3)
  - Ann Street, Ann Arbor, 153) (Box 3)
  - Main Street, Ann Arbor (taken from Liberty Street), 154) (Box 3)
  - Unidentified Road, Ann Arbor, 155) (Box 3)